RAMITH HETTIARACHCHI

+1 (857) • • • − • • • • • ■ Email: im@ramith.fyi • 🎓 website • 🦸 github

SUMMARY

I am passionate towards using machine learning for scientific advancements (especially towards advancing biology and healthcare) while making sure these models are robust, interpretable and equitable.

Research Interests: Computational Biology Robust, Fair, Interpretable ML Uncertainty Quantification Self-Supervised Learning

EDUCATION

University of Moratuwa

B.Sc. Eng(Hons.) Electronic & Telecommunication Engineering

Moratuwa, Sri Lanka Oct 2017 - June 2022

Dean's List: Semesters 1,2,3,4,6,7,8
 Thesis Title: "A Novel Hardware Accelerated Imaging Cytometry Modality Using Diffractive Deep Neural Networks (D2NNs)"

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

July 2022 - Present

Post Baccalaureate Fellow, Division of Science, Harvard University

With the guidance of Dr. Sergey Ovchinnikov, I am developing a differentiable approach for phylogenetic inference. Furthermore, I am developing quantization-aware training methods and robust optical neural networks under the guidance of Dr. Dushan Wadduwage.

Ост 2020 - Mar 2021

Research Intern at CSIRO Data61, Australia

The project involved real-time machine vision with a focus on 3D reconstruction from Intel Realsense D435 camera and performing dynamic obstacle avoidance.

JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- [1] A. Ahmad, **R. Hettiarachchi***, A. Khezri*, B. S. Ahluwalia, D.N. Wadduwage, R. Ahmad, "Highly sensitive quantitative phase microscopy and deep learning complement whole genome sequencing for rapid detection of infection and antimicrobial resistance," *Frontiers in Microbiology (2023).* doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2023.1154620
- [2] H. Arguello, J. Bacca, H. Kariyawasam, E. Vargas, M. Marquez, **R. Hettiarachchi**, H. Garcia, K. Herath, U. Haputhanthri, B. S. Ahluwalia, P. So, D. N. Wadduwage, C. U. S. Edussooriya, "Deep Optical Coding Design in Computational Imaging". *IEEE Signal Processing Magazine, Jan 2023.* doi.org/10.1109/MSP.2022.3200173

 → Tutorial Paper

CONFERENCE/WORKSHOP PUBLICATIONS

- [1] **R. Hettiarachchi**, Avi Swartz, S. Ovchinnikov, "Differentiable Search of Evolutionary Trees" → Accepted to **International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML) 2023 Workshops** "Sampling and Optimization in Discrete Space" (SODS) and "Differentiable Almost Everything" (DiffAE). doi.org/10.1101/2023.07.23.550206 → Evolutionary Biology Soft Combinatorial Optimization Phylogenetic Inference
- [2] R. Hettiarachchi, U. Haputhanthri, K. Herath, H. Kariyawasam, S. Munasinghe, K. Wickramasinghe, D. Samarasinghe, A. C. De Silva and C. U. S. Edussooriya, "A Novel Transfer Learning Based Approach for Screening Pre-existing Heart Diseases using Synchronized ECG Signals and Heart Sounds," *IEEE International Symposium on Circuits and Systems (ISCAS)*, 2021, pp. 1-5, doi.org/10.1109/ISCAS51556.2021.9401093.
 - \hookrightarrow Transfer-learning ECG \leftrightarrow PCG CNN
- [3] S. Rajapakshe, **R. Hettiarachchi**, "Design and Development of a Research Oriented Low Cost Robotics Platform with a Novel Dynamic Global Path Planning Approach," *2022 8th International Conference on Control, Automation and Robotics (ICCAR)*, *2022*, pp. 71-76, doi.org/10.1109/ICCAR55106.2022.9782663. \hookrightarrow Path-planning Visualization C++

INVITED TALKS

- [1] "Towards Realizable Optical Meta-surfaces through Physics-informed Quantization Aware Training", Northeast Symposium on Biomedical Optics Nov, 2022 MIT, Lansdowne St. [link]
- [2] "Towards Realizable D2NN Designs Through Quantization Aware Training", Nano-SymBioSys workshop at UiT, The Arctic University of Norway Sep, 2022 Tromsø, Norway. [link]

PATENT APPLICATIONS

[1] K. Herath*, U. Haputhanthri*, **R. Hettiarachchi***, H. Kariyawasam*, A. Ahmad, B. S. Ahluwalia, C. U. S. Edussooriya and D. Wadduwage, "Provisional Application – Harvard Ref. No. HU 8932 - F&L Ref. 098930-0366 "Differentiable Microscopy Designs an All-Optical Quantitative Phase Microscope".

OTHER RESEARCH PROJECTS

Configuring an Intelligent Reflecting (IRS) Surface for Wireless Communications

FEB - JUNE, 2021

Supervisor : Dr. Prathapasinghe Dharmawansa, University of Moratuwa.

▶ Developed an alternative optimization procedure based on a genetic algorithm and the adaptive moment estimation optimizer to find optimized IRS configurations in a 2⁴⁰⁹⁶ search space. It provided the best data rate and computational cost trade-off, and was the winning solution of the IEEE Signal Processing Cup 2021.

Python Genetic algorithm based optimization Mathematical Modeling

Realtime Sign Language Translation to Speech

Jul - Nov, 2019

Self supervised project.

▶ Developed a solution capable of mapping the EMG signals obtained by an arm to sign language gestures using an ML model. For high-performance inference, the DE-10 Nano field-programmable gate array is used. Project won the Iron Award at the APAC Finals of innovate FPGA, a global FPGA design contest organized by Intel.

C++ SciPy Electromyography (EMG)

Honors, Awards, and Competitions

Scholar - 2022 Princeton Pathways to Graduate School program	2022
Winner - IEEE Signal Processing Cup, ICASSP - $Team T^3$	2021
1st Runner Up - IEEE CASS COVID-19 Special Student Design Competition	2020
2nd Runner Up - IEEE IAS CMD Humanitarian Contest	2020
1st in Sri Lanka, 48th in the World - IEEEXtreme 13.0 Competitive Programming - Team Siraa [link]	2019
APAC - Iron Award - InnovateFPGA - Global FPGA Design Contest	2019
Sri Lankan Team Reserve - International Olympiad in Informatics (IOI)	2015
Bronze Medal - 'Young Computer Scientist' (YCS) Competition	2012,2013
Bronze Medal - 'Junior Inventor of the Year' (JIY) Competition	2010

VOLUNTEER / LEADERSHIP

Project Aya, Cohere For AI	Contributing to Sinhala Language Datasets	2023
NeurIPS Conference	Student Volunteer	2021
IEEE SIGNAL PROCESSING SOCIETY, UOM.	Vice-Chairman, Chairman	2020 - 2022
ROTARACT CLUB OF UNIV. OF MORATUWA	Volunteer, Senior Director - IT	2019 - 2021
Sustainable Education Foundation	Assistant Program Manager - ScholarX	2020 - 2021
Socratic.org	Helping students with Chemistry & Math	2014 - 2016

Programming Proficiency

LANGUAGES: C/C++, Python, Scilab, MATLAB, Mathematica.

VISUALIZATION/TECHNICAL: Javascript, Processing, Git, LATEX.

LIBRARIES: OpenCV, PyTorch, Tensorflow, JAX.

Relevant Coursework

SIGNAL PROCESSING: Genomic Signal Processing BM4321 (A+), Digital Signal Processing EN2570 (A),

Random Signals and Processes EN2040 (A), Signals and Systems EN1060 (A-)

MATHEMATICS: Calculus MA2023 (A+), Graph Theory MA2053 (A+), Linear Algebra MA2033 (A+)

COMPUTER VISION Fundamentals of Image Processing and Machine Vision EN2550 (A),

Machine Vision EN4553 (A+), Advances in Machine Vision EN4583 (A+)

References available upon request.

August, 2023